FRANCIS KODWO BAFFOE

DATA ENGINEER/ANALYST

CONTACT

- London, UK
- francisbff@yahoo.com
- +44 (0) 7474 862030
- in linkedin.com/in/francisbaffoe

EXPERTISE

- •••• Microsoft Azure
- • • Object Oriented Programming
- •••• Python
- •••• SQL
- •••• Hadoop
- •••• SQL Server
- •••• ETL
- •••• Agile Approach
- •••• Hybride Approach
- •••• Git
- •••• Machine Learning

EXECUTIVE SUMMARY

A highly driven and versatile Software Engineer with good experience supporting large-scale software development and carrying out self-led research. I have had the chance to work with different programming languages, hardware and Cloud Platform and I am able to adapt quickly to new ones. I consider myself to be a co-operative and enthusiastic team player, who is dedicated to doing a good job. My communication skills are very good and I learn quickly using my own initiative.

EDUCATION HISTORY

May 2017- June 2019: MSc Software Engineering, University of Liverpool

- Involved in various projects during the course, for instance the structural design and development of an online flight booking system.
- Designed patterns for ATM usage through facades and different model views that permits different types of usage on a typical ATM machine.
- Objected- oriented programming were deployed to structure storage management systems capable of managing large data sets.
- Utilised Hadoop to create, modify, store and retrieve large data sets provided by the university for the purpose of studies.

Dissertation was based on project management effectiveness on small/midsized software development organisations focusing deeply on relevant processes and practices for successful software development project.

September 2010- June 2013: BEng Aerospace Engineering, Queen Mary University of London.

Studied and acquired in-depth understanding of the aerospace industry including all the fundamental of how an Aircraft is designed and operated successfully.

- Communication & Presentation gained during degree and numerous work experiences where technical, clear and concise reports and presentation was vital.
- Organisation, Time & Project Management ability to organise and prioritise work, accordingly, ensuring successful completion of tasks on time and within budget. Skills developed whilst completing several academic and work projects.
- Analytical Thinking & Problem Solving quantitative background with keen attention to detail ensuring accurate analysis.
- Teamwork able to adapt in a team environment and lead when required as reflected by my diverse background. Also encourages the achievement of others in a team.

Dissertation was based on the stimulation of airflow around a symmetric object using Computational Fluid Dynamics to analyses laminar and turbulent flows relating to aircraft structures.

- • • Communication
- •••• Problem Solving
- • Leadership
- •••• Judgement and Decision Making
- •••• End-to-End Project Planning
- •••• Advanced Microsoft Excel User

ATTRIBUTES









WORK EXPERIENCE

Data Engineer/Analyst, August 2017- November 2019 JD Wetherspoon

- Developed modelling framework in python to show potential of 10% improvement in sales per customer with incremental revenue.
- Leveraged rule-based extraction engines and resemble of machine learning models to predict likelihood of customer making a purchase.
- Developed forecasting models to forecast daily, weekly, and monthly operational performance.
- Used big data tools to interact with Hadoop data lake for data transformation.
- Performed ETL on disparate data sources like online transaction, payment, order history and marketing campaigns data to provide customer insights.
- Extracted data from management information system into excel.
- Analysed data in revenue, refunds, profit, opportunity, and risks from different dimensions by time, product, channel, account, and others.
- Developed performance management models to calculate KPI measures and track sales performance.
- Improved 10% per month sales revenue by drawing utilising sales performance reports and strategy optimisations.
- Utilised distribution systems and built data pipelines to determine product impacts on different marketing channels and proposed solutions to drive impact for intensive analyses.

Data Analyst, June 2016- July 2017 HMRC

- Worked closely with stakeholders in understanding their data sources and attributes while designing ETL mapping documents.
- Apache Sqoop was used to export data from structured datastores into Hadoop.
- Using Apache Hive, external tables were built on top of files for querying and analysis.
- External tables were used as there was a clear requirement for the data to be retained.
- Queriedx data using Hive.

Data Visualisation, October 2015 - July 2016 EDF Utility Company

- Engaged with senior management to develop BI dashboards for one of Europe's largest infrastructure projects.
- Designed and developed APIs using Mulesoft and Java reading data from the cloud for feeding into visualisations.
- Explored Tableau, developed dashboards in QlikView and HTML, JavaScript, D3, R and Shin.